Josh Rayman

linkedin.com/in/joshrayman

josh@rayman.xyz

Graphics/Data Visualisation Developer

Four years' experience writing data vis/interactive JavaScript content. Interested in storytelling using web technology and turning data into graphics – finding the visual angle, wrangling data, and writing performant code. I have also worked on two greenfield projects as the first hired front-end developer, providing me with experience in building things fast, well, and to a demanding deadline.

Areas of expertise include:

- Graphics development
- Data analysis
- Storytelling
- Cartography
- Mobile-first/UX design
- Internationalisation
- Accessibility
- SPA development
 - Cross-browser support
 Product development
 Product development

 Project management

 Node.is
- Data visualisation
- Cloud infrastructure
- Serverless computing

Professional Experience

BBC - Visual Journalism Developer

August 2017 - Current

Developer for the newly created World Service Visual Journalism team, building mobile-first interactive content for websites in the Near East region. I have been involved in pitching and building interactive features for BBC Arabic, Persian, Turkish, Pashto, Uzbek and Kyrgyz.

I am focused on internationalisation, page performance and right-to-left CSS/SVG code, tailoring the tech stack for each project using ES6, d3.js and reusing internal modules built for previous BBC output.

Key Contributions:

- Researched and built multiple products covering the snap 2018 Turkish elections, moving quickly to deliver content prior to the election and producing a results dashboard.
- Built and maintained a serverless social media statistics collector for the BBC Persian service which was used internally by the audience engagement team.
- Built an interactive product about the Iran nuclear deal for BBC Persian to a short and shifting deadline.

Amalytics - Front-end Lead Developer

August 2016 - August 2017

Start-up fintech company producing IT resourcing software used by a FTSE100 Company. Front-end lead/d3.js developer for data visualisation project management platform, including line management of two front-end developers.

Key Contributions:

- Developed a dynamic tabular view of the dataset to save analysts' time verifying data.
- Regularly involved in product development decisions, steering the visualisation decisions towards using appropriate charts for the data.

Cascade.bi - Software Developer

September 2014 - August 2016

Front-end lead for SaaS business intelligence platform, building an ASP.net single page application and responsive dashboards using dc.js/d3.js. Involved with the full application lifecycle, from prototypes that were used to secure early funding through to beta deployment.

Key Contributions:

• Designed Node.js server side data aggregation solution to process datasets.

Technical Skills and Education

Languages HTML5, CSS3/SASS, ES6/ES5 JavaScript, SVG, C#, SQL, Python, R

Frameworks d3.js, Vue.js, Greensock.js (animation), Handlebars, Razor, Angular 1.x,

jQuery, Bootstrap, Node.js

Tools Testing (Karma, Mocha, Chai, Sinon, Nightwatch), AWS, Git, CI

(Jenkins), Illustrator, Photoshop, QGIS, Docker, Grunt, Yeoman

Project Agile, Scrum, TDD/BDD (Cucumber/Gherkin), sprint planning and

Management coordination, stakeholder management.

Education

Masters of Music (by Research) - Electro-Acoustic Composition and Sonic Arts

University of East Anglia

Research project on interactive video game music, producing a project that involved writing real-time data interfaces (C++, JS) to create a portfolio of generated music.

Presented research at two Ludomusicology Conferences, and participated in the university Sonic Arts Ensemble as performer/composer.

BA (Hons) - Music (2:1)

University of East Anglia

Studied computer music and composition, and wrote a dissertation on the performing practices of silent film era musicians in cinemas.